<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the House of Peeres, in the Abbey at Westminster, the 26. of Novemb. 1645. Being the day appointed for solemne and publique humiliation. / By Jer: Burroughes. Published by order of the said House.</title>
            <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E310_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861190</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77999)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E310[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the House of Peeres, in the Abbey at Westminster, the 26. of Novemb. 1645. Being the day appointed for solemne and publique humiliation. / By Jer: Burroughes. Published by order of the said House.</title>
                  <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 [i.e. 50] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Dawlman.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVI. [1646, i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy in late 1645. Wing has 1646; the McAlpin Catalogue lists under 1646.</note>
                  <note>Page 50 is misnumbered 38.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the I in imprint date is crossed out; "1645".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians IV, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:113318:1"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Iovis</hi> 27. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1645.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament, That M. <hi>Burroughes,</hi> who Preached yeſterday in the Abby-Church <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> before the Lords in Parliament, being the day of the Publique Faſt, is hereby thanked for the great pains he took in the ſaid Sermon; And deſired to Print and Publiſh the ſame; which is onely to be Printed by Authority under his own hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io: Browne, Cleric. Parliamentorum.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>I appoint</hi> Robert Dawlman <hi>to print this Sermon, and no other.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Jer: Burroughes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113318:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, The Houſe of <hi>PEERES,</hi> aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od calls you to dayes of Faſting and Prayer, you call his Miniſters to joyn with you, to be helpfull to you in them. When ſhould you ever think to be dealt faithfully with, if not now? How can we recompence better any faithfulneſſe of yours to God and the State, but by being faithfull to your ſoules? Theſe Prayers and Sermons paſſe away moneth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moneth, but know, that God will call them all over againe, he will require an account of them one day. It is a happineſſe you have beyond the greateſt part of the Nobility of the Chriſtian world, that you have the Word in the plainneſſe and power of it adminiſtred to you. You cannot honour the Word ſo much as it honours you; the Preachers of the Word have not ſo much need of you, as you have of that Word they preach to you. Your Honours have the largeſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to honour God, and to doe good to his Saints, that ever Noblemen had ſince the world began. God hath laid out work for you fit for truly noble ſpirits; you have as many Saints to take care of in theſe Kingdomes, as ever any on earth had, uſe them kindly, that they may bleſſe you, and bleſſe God for you; be not exaſperated againſt any of them by thoſe who know not, or conſider not of what ſpirits they are. Although we ſhould account it a heaven upon earth that there were nothing but wheat growing in that part of the field where we live; yet ſeeing there are many tares ſprung up, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errors and ſinfull practices; if your Lordſhips ſhould now be put
<pb facs="tcp:113318:2"/> upon ſuch ſeverity, as out of zeale to pluck up all the errors which are not venemous weeds deſtroying, but tares onely, ſome way diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the growth of the wheat, you ſhall as much as in you lies pluck up much of the wheat, denying ſuch as are godly and peaceable the enjoyment of the Ordinances of Chriſt, (for ſo it is, if they cannot partake of them, without that which is ſinne to them) and as ſome would have it, caſt them out of the Kingdome: This, I feare, will not be acceptable to the meek, gentle, forbearing ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, in the day of your account.</p>
            <p>For connivence at Blaſphemies or damnable Hereſies, God forbid any ſhould open his mouth; thoſe who are guilty herein againſt the light of nature, ſhould be taken off from the face of the earth; and ſuch as are guilty againſt ſupernaturall light, are to be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and kept from the ſociety of men, that they infect not others. But if on the other ſide, your Lordſhips be put upon this principle, that thoſe who appeare to be men holy and gracious, yet muſt not be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in opinion or practice wherein they differ from what ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of learned and godly men ſhall determine. The Lord prepare me for himſelfe, and quickly call me out of this world, that my eyes may not behold ſuch a ſad ſpectacle, as the hard uſage (to ſay no worſe) of ſo many thouſands of Saints, and that by ſuch who are alſo I beleeve the true Saints of God.</p>
            <p>When I look upward to God, to your Honours, and the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, I ſee leſſe cauſe of feare: God is full of mercy, love, patience, and tenderneſſe towards thoſe who are godly, and deſire to walk peaceably with his Saints; if they can appeale to him; Oh Lord, the ſearcher of the ſecrets of hearts, thou knoweſt not onely our deſires, but our painfull ſincere endeavours, are to find out thy mind, and to ſubmit our underſtandings, wills, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, practiſes, to whatſoever in the uſe of any means, we can ſee to be thy will: but after all our diligent endeavours, we yet cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſuch opinions and practiſes, which our brethren hold forth to us to be what thou requireſt of us; and thou chargeſt us not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge or practiſe any thing, where we feel not a bottome of thy Word to reſt upon; therefore if it be through our weakneſſe that we doe not joyne with our brethren in what they would have, yet out of a ſincere deſire that we may doe nothing diſpleaſing to thee, Lord pardon this to us: Surely God in this caſe will pitty his people, he will not charge ſuch errour, in judgement or practice upon them.</p>
            <p>And as for your Honours, together with the Honourable Houſe
<pb facs="tcp:113318:2"/> of Commons, we have that which cannot but be a comfort to thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of truly godly people in the land, for which they praiſe God. Namely, an Order from you that the Committe of Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons appointed to treat with the Commiſsioners of Scotland, and the Committee of the Aſſembly doe endeavour the finding out ſome way how farre tender conſciences who cannot in all things ſubmit to the common rule, may be tolerated according to the word of God; Wee ſee in your Lordſhips and the Honourable Houſe of Commons, a Nobleneſſe, joyned with much tenderneſſe to the godly party, whom God hath made ſo inſtrumentall for you; for which, the bleſſing of God be upon you, and your poſterities. But it cannot but much ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den our hearts, that any party in the Kingdom ſhould ſeek to quench that ſparke of favour and hope, that ſo good a hand of God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to kindle, for his people who feare him. Yea, that ſo many of our brethren who lately were under bondage, with whom we joyned in faſting and prayer, crying to heaven for deliverance from our yokes; and that thoſe who awhile ſince were left deſtitute, and fled to this City for refuge from the rage of the enemy: yet as ſoon as they have found ſuccour here, that they ſhould riſe up to oppoſe a forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their brethren, who together with them love Ieſus Chriſt, and agree with them in the ſubſtance of worſhip, and the doctrinall part of Religion; yea, and in matter of Diſcipline differ not from them but in that which is controverſall; not ſo cleare to themſelves, but that they will acknowledge, godly and peacable men may miſtake in; what no forbearance in theſe things? How comes this hardneſſe, this ſeverity, into thoſe hearts, where the ſpirit of Ieſus Chriſt rules? where are thoſe bowels? thoſe bowels they ſay are ſo ſtirred in them, ſurely there is want of bowels, or if they be there, Oh that they would worke ſome other way then yet they have done. Nay further, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but goe to our hearts, to ſee theſe brethren to ſtirre up the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and City againſt them who love them in the Lord;<note place="margin">Si tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet pondus aliquod verum, ut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res diſcentis excedat, ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum eſt, ut extendat creſcentem, non imponendum, ut obterat par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulum. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Queſt. in <hi>Mat. 11.</hi>
               </note> and to be ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement to promote that, which very lately many, if not moſt of them underſtood not, of which they have given out no Modell to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with proofes and reaſons. If I know mine own heart, I can ſay, Peace is dearer to me then my life, I could joyfully lay down my life to procure peace between brethren, but ſurely this is not the way.</p>
            <p>It is a good rule of <hi>Auguſtine, If any truth hath that weight, that it exceeds the ſtrength of the learner; it is to be ſuſpended, that that which is little and tender, may have liberty by degrees to put forth it ſelfe; it muſt not be impoſed, left it bruiſe and oppreſſe it, and ſo hinder the growth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113318:3"/>
            <p>Whatſoever liberty ſhall be granted according to the Word, I hope there is a generation that will not abuſe it, but will in the middeſt of their liberties be ſervants to Peace and Concord, according to that I find in an Epiſtle of Maſter <hi>Calvins</hi> to <hi>Farell, Nos liberi, Servi ſumus Pacis &amp; Concordiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And my Lords, ſeeing there is ſuch an out-cry againſt Toleration and Schiſme, I beſeech your Honours that there may be a full debate, how far Chriſt would have Brethren tolerate one another, both in matters of judgement and practice; and what that Schiſme is, which the Scripture condemnes as a thing not to be ſuffered, and that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of this debate may be publiſhed to the Kingdome for their ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. We know what abuſe there hath been of words, by them a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of oppoſition hath been ſtirred up in people againſt they know not what. And I the rather humbly beſeech this, becauſe many preſume to interpret the Covenant againſt all kind of Toleration, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are pleaſed to call Schiſme, and ſo they make the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which we have made with the high God, to become a ſnare to many thouſand conſciences of godly and peaceable men.</p>
            <p>The Lord God guide your Honours, and give unto every one of you the wiſdome of an Angel of God, in theſe miſerable diſtracting times, that you may doe worthily in your generation, that in all your wayes Chriſt may owne you, and all the godly of the Land may with one ſpirit joyne together and bleſſe you, which is and ſhall be the prayer of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours In all humble ſervice for Chriſt,</hi> Jer: Burroughes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113318:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED at a late FAST, before the Right Honourable the Houſe of PEERES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHILIP. 4.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I know both how to be abaſed, and I know how to abound: every where, and in all things I am inſtructed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides the Apoſtolicall call <hi>Paul</hi> had to preach to all Nations, he had a ſpeciall extraordinary call to preach to theſe Philippians. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.9. <hi>A man of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia appeares in a viſion, and prayed him, ſaying, Come over into Macedonia and help us.</hi> By which, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>he aſſuredly gathered that the Lord had called him to preach the Goſpel there.</hi> The firſt place in Macedonia where he preached, was Philippi, a chiefe City in that part of Macedonia, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. But was <hi>Pauls</hi> encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to what might have been expected from his extraordinary call? one would have thought the people ſhould have come preſently in to embrace the Goſpel. And when I conſider of this place, <hi>[Weſtminſter]</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113318:4"/> the extraordinary hand of God in bringing the Goſpel to be preached to you here in power, theſe thoughts preſently ariſe, there is hope that there are many ſoules here that belong to Gods election, ſurely many will come in and embrace the Goſpel here. Who could have thought ſix yeeres ſince, that inſtead of every mornings chanting, this place ſhould be the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for having the Goſpel preached in it? I think I may ſay of any place in all the world. How extraordinary hath the providence of God been towards you, in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thus for you! One would think now the hearts of people ſhould be mightily ſtirred; God forbid the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe here ſhould be no better then <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching at Philippi was at the firſt. For the firſt Sabbath he came thither, he went to a Rivers ſide to preach; and what, did the Nobles, the Magiſtrates, the Gentry, the chiefe Citizens come out to heare him? No, onely a few women came to him: <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>We ſpake</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>to the women which reſorted thither. Paul</hi> is a womans Preacher. Well, but did the Word work upon any of the women? Yes, <hi>There was a certaine woman named Lydia, a trades-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a ſeller of purple, whoſe heart the Lord opened.</hi> But though he had no better ſucceſſe at the firſt, yet after perhaps he might.</p>
            <p>The next thing that you heare of him, is, that he, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Silas</hi> who went along with him, is drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged before the Magiſtrates for factious troublers of the Citie, the rude multitude are raiſed againſt them. The Magiſtrates look upon them as men moſt vile and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of horrid things, ſo as they are inraged againſt them; they rend off their clothes, and whip them, they put them into priſon, they are thruſt into the dungeon, and put into the ſtocks: and is this the fruit of that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full call of God, of that viſion from heaven, that did ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113318:4"/> encourage <hi>Paul,</hi> a man of ſuch a mighty Apoſtolicall ſpirit as he had, to come to this place to preach?</p>
            <p>Oh the ſad diſcouragements that ſome meet with, in works that God calls them unto! Learn by this never to conclude that a work is not of God, becauſe you meet with diſcouragements at the firſt. Bare your hearts upon Gods call, there will come forth good at the laſt.</p>
            <p>The ſpirits of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were not daunted by this hard ſucceſſe; for 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. he tells us, that <hi>After they were ſhamefully intreated at Philippi, they were bold in their God</hi> There was as famous a Church gathered in Philippi at the laſt, as free from mixture, as eminent in godlineſſe as any. That way men ſleight, contemne, caſt dirt upon, ſtirre up Magiſtrates and people againſt, may prevaile at laſt. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. <hi>Paul thanks God for them upon every remembrance of them, alwaies in every prayer, he makes his requeſt for them with joy.</hi> Oh that thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters whom God ſends to you to preach every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, might from that they ſee in you ſay thus: Every time we think of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> we give God thanks, we cannot but remember that place with joy, in regard of the happy ſucceſſe of our Miniſtery there. But though theſe Philippians were ſtirred at firſt, did thoſe workings of the Goſpel upon them hold? Many have hopefull workings upon them, when the Goſpel comes firſt among them; but after a while all vaniſhes and comes to nothing: but it was not ſo here, for <hi>ver.</hi> 5. he ſayes, <hi>Their fellowſhip in the Goſpell had continued from the firſt day untill now,</hi> which was about ten yeares: For <hi>Pauls</hi> firſt comming to Philippi was in the 7. of <hi>Claudius,</hi> and this Epiſtle was wrote in the 3. of <hi>Nero.</hi> Many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at their firſt gathering have ſweet fellowſhip, but in leſſe then five yeeres it is much interrupted by diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113318:5"/> the glory of it is much darkned.</p>
            <p>At this time Paul was in priſon at Rome. Theſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians hearing it, having received the Goſpel by his Miniſtery, ſend <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> their Miniſter to viſit him, and by him they ſend reliefe to his neceſſities. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſufferings did not take off their hearts from him or his doctrine. It is not the way to prevail againſt Saints, againſt truths, or wayes of God, to uſe violence againſt them; hypocrites may be taken off that way, but thoſe who are ſound, will be the more confirmed.</p>
            <p>Now upon the Philippians ſending to relieve him in priſon, <hi>Paul</hi> takes this occaſion to write this Epiſtle to them, wherein he manifeſts his rejoycing at their care of him: but becauſe ſome might think he loved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive gifts from them, (which indeed are oftentimes ſnares, not onely to the miniſters of Juſtice, but to the miniſters of the Goſpel) No, ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi> it is not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of want that I thus write to you, want troubles me not, doe not think that I deſire to gaine by my impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for <hi>I have learned in whatſoever ſtate I am therewith to be content.</hi> Let it be want or not, it makes no great difference in my eſtate, for <hi>I know how to be abaſed, and how to abound: in every thing I am inſtructed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know.</hi> Humility is a knowing grace. <hi>Paul</hi> would not in a fooliſh ſordid way debaſe himſelfe, neither would he venture himſelfe ſillily; I know when God calls me to ſuffer, then I will ſuffer; and when God doth not, then I will not. <hi>I know how to be abaſed.</hi> Humility is not unlearned.<note place="margin">Non indocta humilitas, ſed quae habet ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam laudi datur eſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militas formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis, imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </note> There is a humility of feare, and of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and unskilfulneſſe, but this is a knowing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I have known it, I have been acquainted with this, I am not now to learn it. When God firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me, he ſhewed me what things I muſt ſuffer for his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113318:5"/> Name, it is not a leſſon now to learne, <hi>I know how to be abaſed,</hi> I have learned in the ſchoole of Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even to be trampled under feet.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quaſi <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternat.</note> A godly heart is willing to lye under the feet of any for good. <hi>I know how.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know how to judge of my abaſement; not to look upon it as ſuch a hideous thing, as carnall hearts would; I can ſee honour to be in my abaſement; I know how to make other interpretations of Gods meaning in my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement then the world does; I know how to beare it with a quiet ſpirit; I know how to ſatisfie my heart in it; I know how to improve it to the glory of God, to the ſpirituall good of mine owne ſoule and others; I know how to exerciſe faith and other graces in it; how to get out the ſting, the venome of it; I know how to carry my ſelfe graciouſly, comfortably, heavenly in my abaſement; ſo as though the world puts diſhonour upon me, I ſhall not by any unbeſeeming carriage diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my ſelfe or my cauſe. And it appears he did know how, for his gracious carriage in his bonds was ſuch, as furthered the converſion of divers, ſome of the Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Caeſars</hi> houſhold, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I know how to abound.</hi> If God ſends in ſupplyes to me, if he gives me reſpect and honour among the Churches, I know who to look up to as the cauſe of all, I know how to carry my ſelfe holily and ſpiritually in the midſt of all my enjoyments; if God ſends me in ſo much as to run over, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I know how to make uſe of it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſicut fons ſcaturiens in ſe aqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non retinet, ſed fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras emittens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undat ad alios. <hi>Zanch. in Phil. c. 1. 9.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every where, and in all things,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, In every place, in every time, in every thing, the words will bear all this. It is a harder thing either to be abaſed, or to abound in one place more then another; in ſome place men may be honoured much in their ſufferings, in other places there will be no regard given to them, yea they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113318:6"/> will be made a ſcorn and contempt in ſome places; there are more and ſtronger temptations to the abuſe of a proſperous condition, then in others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In every time. Some men can carry themſelves ſtoutly in their abaſement at firſt, but after a while it growes too burthenſome to them, they begin to have repenting thoughts, wiſhing they had not engaged themſelves ſo as they have. So ſome are free in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance God hath ſent in, to good uſes at ſome time, but come to them at other times, and they are not the ſame men; but <hi>I have learned how to be abaſed, and how to abound, in every time, and in every thing.</hi> Some can beare abaſement in ſome things, but not in others; ſome can better manage wealth, then honour; others better ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour then wealth: <hi>but I,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul, in every thing am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Am inſtructed,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am taught as in a myſterie, <hi>initiatus myſterius,</hi> I had not this by nature, I am taught it, and I ſee it is a myſterie. It is not through the ſtrength of reaſon I am able to doe this, though that will goe a great way, but it is a great myſterie of godlineſſe to know how to carry ones ſelfe graciouſly, through vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of conditions. It is not through a naturall ſtayednes of temper, nor through a ſturdy reſolution that I wil not be altered, through the variety of conditions I am caſt into, but Jeſus Chriſt hath taught me the art and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this.</p>
            <p>This choſen veſſell of God, ſet apart to doe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſervice for Chriſt that ever man did, was toſſed up and downe in the world, ſometimes he wanted bread, ſometimes he was clothed in ragges, he had not enough to cover his nakedneſſe. Hearken to this you who are delicate in your diet, and brave in your clothes, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but curioſities can content you; here is one who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113318:6"/> did Chriſt more ſervice then a thouſand of you, and yet you ſee what ſerved his turne.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. in Col. Hom. 12</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> makes notable uſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſufferings, to check the vanity and pride of mens hearts, ſet upon delicacies. <hi>Would you</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>be clothed in ſilkes? remember the bands of Paul, and ſilken clothes will be vile unto thee. Would you be beſpangled with gold? remember the bands of Paul. Would you be brave with your haire?</hi> (we may ſay now with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens, nay with other womens haire, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed your own heire by your luſts) <hi>conſider</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>of the filth and deformity of Paul in priſon. Would you have ſweet oyntments and powders? chooſe rather Pauls tears.</hi> And for diſhonour, he tells us that he and thoſe who joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him, were accounted the off-ſcouring &amp; filth of all things, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rejectamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo Eraſmus.</note> it ſignifies the dirt ſcraped off mens ſhooes, or from the pavement of the ground; he hath reference to that, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.45. <hi>Thou haſt made us the off-ſcouring and refuſe in the midſt of the people,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeam,</hi> ſo <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> turnes it, the loathing of the people, their ſtomachs were ready to turne when they ſaw them, when they thought or ſpake of them, as when a man is ready to vomit. And <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the filth gathered by ſweepings up and downe, and caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the common dung-cart in the ſtreet. <hi>Budaeus</hi> thinks theſe words have reference to the cuſtome of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, who in times of infectious diſeaſes or publike ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, ſacrificed certaine men to their gods, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving thoſe evils that were upon them, and upon theſe men they lay all the execrations of the people, as if they had been the cauſes of all their miſery: <hi>So are we accounted,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi> men cry out of us as the plague of the world, they curſe us as the plague of all their miſery. At other times, <hi>Paul</hi> had honour enough: <hi>Gal</hi> 4.15. <hi>Where is the bleſſedneſſe? I beare you record, you would have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113318:7"/> plucked out your owne eyes, and have given them to me.</hi> They turned upon their owne heads, ſayes <hi>Luther</hi> upon the place, the cruell hatred and indignation both of Jews and Gentiles, becauſe they were the receivers and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancers of <hi>Paul:</hi> So at this day (ſayes he) the name of <hi>Luther</hi> is moſt odious in the world, he that praiſeth me, ſinneth worſe then an Idolater, blaſphemer, perjurer, adulterer, murtherer, theefe: it muſt needs be therefore (ſayes he) the Galatians were well eſtabliſhed in the faith of Chriſt, ſeeing they with ſo much danger recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Paul.</hi> It hath been the honour of ſome of you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore to receive and countenance godly Miniſters, who ſuffered under the tyrannie of Prelates; you were willing to venture the diſcountenance of the times in owning them. This Chriſt hath owned you for, and we hope it ſhall be remembred for good to you and yours. Let not your hearts be changed towards theſe men.</p>
            <p>If you think or ſay, Now the caſe is altered, they ſtood out then againſt Prelates and Innovations, now they hinder Reformation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>That which ſome call a hinderance of Reformation, it may be Chriſt another day will call by another name, a conſcientious ſeeking to know his mind, and a ſincere endeavour to come up the neareſt to the rule of his Word.</p>
            <p>Doe not theſe men in the change of times and variety of conditions that God hath caſt them into, keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant evenneſſe in their reſpects to God, and their holy walking before him? It argues an excellency of ſpirit to be acted by ſuch principles as carries the heart and life on in a gracious even courſe through changes of times and variety of conditions. Some men know not how to manage any condition, they are never well ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther full or faſting, as we uſe to ſay. As <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſaid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113318:7"/> of <hi>Marcellus, Nec bonam nec malam fortunam ferre potuit;</hi> but Grace knowes how to manage every condition. That Ship is well ballaſted that ſayles cleaverly, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much toſſed with winds and waves. It is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of grace to be able to turne this way or that way, as God calls, to make uſe of the weapons of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, both on the right hand and on the left.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.7.</note> Truth and falſhood, good and evill are at ſuch a diſtance, as by the ſame principle a man cannot apply himſelf to either ſide; but as for honour or diſhonour, poverty or riches, liberty or reſtraint, they are at no ſuch diſtance, but that the ſame grace may apply it ſelfe this way or that way, as occaſion ſerves.</p>
            <p>We reade of that Grace, <hi>(Hope)</hi> ſometimes it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Helmet,</hi> ſometimes an <hi>Anchor;</hi> if you be at land, and meet with enemies, Hope is your Helmet; if at ſea, and meet with ſtormes, Hope is your Anchor. Like <hi>Mertylus</hi> his ſhield, which after the uſe he had of it in the field, having it with him at ſea, and ſuffering ſhip-wrack, it ſerved him for a boat to waffe him to ſhore. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108. you ſhall find <hi>Davids</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition various, but his ſpirit the ſame. In the 57. he is fled for his life from the rage of <hi>Saul,</hi> and hid in a cave; in 108. he is triumphing, <hi>God hath ſpoken in his holineſſe, I will rejoyce, I will divide Shechem, I will mete out the valley of Succoth. Gilead is mine, Manaſſeh is mine, Ephraim is the ſtrength of my head, Moab is my waſhpot, &amp;c.</hi> yet a great part of theſe Pſalmes is in the very ſame words, <hi>My heart is fixed, my heart is fixed, to God will I ſing and give praiſe, &amp;c.</hi> from the 7. <hi>ver.</hi> in the 57. to the end; and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108. from the 1. to the 7. <hi>ver.</hi> It is a great part of the glory of God to be unchangeable, and yet to operate in all changes. It is a great excellency of the image of God in the hearts of the Saints, that in the variety of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113318:8"/> conditions it ſtil abides the ſame, to <hi>know how to be abaſed,</hi> and <hi>how to abound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the two great Leſſons in the Text, <hi>Paul</hi> had learned them both. We reade <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. <hi>Agur,</hi> though wiſe and godly, yet he deſired to have neither riches nor poverty; he was afraid of abaſement, or abounding; but the Goſpel gives higher degrees of grace, <hi>Paul</hi> was afraid of neither, he knew how to manage either abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or abounding. Both theſe Leſſons doe nearly concern this Honourable Auditory; of both, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is moſt difficult, in which we ſhall be largeſt.</p>
            <p>The greateſt on the earth had need learn how to be abaſed: God knowes how to abaſe you thouſands of wayes, but you muſt know how to be abaſed, it were happy if you did.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know therefore that there is an infinite diſtance between God and you. What are you, though Nobles, Earles, yea though you were the Lords of the whole earth, but poore vile wormes, under the feet of the Almighty? You love to have men know their diſtance between you and them; it is fit it ſhould be ſo; it is your due, their duty; but doe you know alſo the infinite diſtance there is between the high God and you: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus, Valentinianus, Theodoſius,</hi> three Emperours, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves <hi>Vaſallos Chriſti,</hi> Chriſts vaſſals, ſuch is the diſtance between him and the greateſt Emperours, as it is their honour to ſtand even in that relation to him. Had you all your former Lands, Poſſeſſions, Honours, were they encreaſed a thouſand fold, yet one ſight of the glory of the great God were enough to abaſe your hearts to the duſt.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially when you come into Gods preſence, you muſt be ſure to have your hearts abaſed before him; Let not your thoughts, your eyes wander in Prayer; let
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113318:8"/> there be no whiſperings, no carriage unbeſeeming the preſence of the great God: And in hearing the Word, your hearts muſt lye low. It is true, the condition of the Meſſenger is beneath you, but the word he brings is above you; God expects you ſhould heare his word with trembling hearts. It may be ſome Trencher-Chaplains preaching to ſome of you, have out of hope of preferments by you, laboured to ſatisfie your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which hath made ſome of you ſleight the Word; but when the Word is ſpoken as the Word of God unto you, he expects your hearts ſhould fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and yeeld due ſubjection to it. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> a great King is charged for this, that he did not humble himſelfe before <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet. <hi>Paul,</hi> a priſoner at the Barre, preaching to <hi>Felix</hi> the Judge, of righteouſneſſe, temperance, and judgement to come, made him tremble upon the Bench, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25. And eſpecially in the dayes of Humiliation, God looks for hearts broken, humbled and abaſed; Take heed theſe dayes be not a meere forme to you; ſeeing you hold forth to the world that you acknowledge God calling you to ſuch dayes, he expects that your ſouls ſhould be afflicted in them, that you ſhould come into and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in his preſence as poore wretches, begging for your lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Lay to heart the vileneſſe of ſinne which hath ſtained your births; your births otherwiſe are honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: but every one of you have your blood ſtained with High Treaſon againſt the God of heaven. The many and foule ſins of your youth and latter time, hath diſhonoured you; all the world cannot put ſuch glory upon you, as ſinne puts baſeneſſe. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> is called a vile perſon, though a great Prince. <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports, that the Samaritans petitioning him,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113318:9"/> ſtyled him <hi>The mighty God;</hi> but the holy Ghoſt loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon him as wicked, ſaith, <hi>he is a vile perſon.</hi> Sin makes thoſe who are otherwiſe honourable, to be vile in the preſence of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And what are thoſe great things you have in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God? <hi>Tantus quiſque eſt, quantus eſt apud Deum;</hi> What a man is to God, ſo indeed he is to be eſteemed. What are houſes or lands, titles or gay clothes to God?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider the ſervice that others doe for God more then you; God hath more honour in one moneth from ſome poore families who work hard to get their bread, then in ſome of yours in many yeares. Now the excellency of men is according to their uſefulnes. That man is the moſt honourable man that is the moſt uſefull man. The Lord hath not been much beholding to the great men of the earth for the carrying on his great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes in the world, eſpecially ſince Chriſts time, except ſome few, they have been laid aſide in the great works that God hath done. <hi>Not many rich, not many noble, but God hath choſen the poore of the world, the vile and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible things of the world, to carry on his moſt precious works by.</hi> This is a humbling conſideration to the great ones of the earth.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Turcium impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium quantum quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca tantum eſt quam paterfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milias proficit canibus.</note>5. All the honours and riches you have, are no other then may be the portion of a Reprobate. True, you have more then others, but not more then a Reprobate may have. <hi>The whole Turkiſh Empire,</hi> ſayes <hi>Luther, is but a crumme that the Maſter of the Family throwes to a dog,</hi> all but a meere phanſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 25.23. <hi>Bernice</hi> and <hi>Agrippa</hi> came with great pomp, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo are the words of the holy Ghoſt. I find after God had rejected <hi>Saul,</hi> yet he lets him proſper much, he had many victories, great riches.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113318:9"/> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. he was rejected, but reade farther, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. Learne then to be abaſed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your greatneſſe in the world.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And if you belong not to God, that title you have to all your greatneſſe is no other then that which a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactour hath to what is given him by the bounty of the Prince, to preſerve him till his execution. I deny not but wicked men have a right not onely before men, but before God to what they enjoy in the world; but it is ſuch a right as the Malefactor hath to what is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him after he hath forfeited all, he does not uſurp it, it is given him. There is little cauſe ſuch ſhould pride themſelves in what they have.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is no long time that you are like to enjoy, that now you have above others; within a while there will be little difference between you and others; onely this, you will have more to anſwer for then others.</p>
            <p>When I appeare before God, ſaies <hi>Pelican,</hi> a German Divine, I ſhall not appeare in my robes as a Doctor, but as a Chriſtian; ſo when you ſhall appeare before Chriſt, you ſhall not appear in your Parliament robes, with your enſignes of honour and Nobilitie, but as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, meane as the pooreſt; onely you muſt anſwer for your honour, your Nobilitie you had here, how they were improved for God. Many men of great eſtates &amp; dignities, when they come to dye, would be glad to be as ſuch and ſuch poor men, who have walked with God in their integritie. <hi>Granatenſis</hi> reports of one <hi>Eucritus,</hi> who being asked, <hi>Uter mallet eſſe Craeſus vel Socrates,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had rather be <hi>Craeſus,</hi> or <hi>Socrates?</hi> he anſwered, <hi>Vivens Craeſus, moriens Socrates;</hi> while he lived, <hi>Craeſus;</hi> when he dyed, <hi>Socrates.</hi> God will have glory from all his creatures; he hath ſworne by himſelf, and the word hath proceeded out of his mouth in righteouſneſſe, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113318:10"/> 
               <hi>Every knee ſhall bow unto him, and every tongue confeſſe his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learne then how to be abaſed now; doe not ſtay till God forces abaſement; if you ſtay till then, God may juſtly refuſe to receive any glory from you, in any other but a paſſive way.</p>
            <p>Baſeneſſe ſhould be fartheſt from the ſpirits of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen; but to know how to be abaſed, that is, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before God, this is a leſſon of great uſe for men of noble families, and noble ſpirits; it will no way hinder the nobleneſſe of your ſpirits, but heighten and enlarge them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A baſe ſpirit ſinks down to low unworthy things, as the adequate object of it; it hath no high or honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſignes for God, or any thing of worth; but if the fleſh may be ſatisfied in the luſts of it, this is all it mindes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A baſe ſpirit is diſcouraged by any difficulties it meets with in the greateſt buſineſſes; it lets the worke goe, rather then it will encounter any difficultie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Baſeneſſe cauſes men to regard onely the ſerving their owne turnes; if they be ſerved, let come of others or publique good what will, they care not.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Baſe ſpirits are led along by every little temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on like fooles, they are not able to withſtand ſcarce any temptation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A baſe ſpirit will inſult over thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath it; but in a vile manner ſubject it ſelf to thoſe who are above it, even to lye under their luſts. God deliver you from this. This need not be learned. The luſts in mens hearts, if let alone, will quickly bring down mens ſpirits to this baſeneſſe. This hath been and is the cauſe of much evill among us: ſuch a baſe ſpirit, oh how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutable is it to a noble birth!</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113318:10"/>
            <p>But by learning this leſſon of the Apoſtle, to be willing to have the heart, the eſtate, name, and whatſoever God pleaſes to lye low before him, this is of great uſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver men in high places from the power of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The temptations are great that you are ſubject to, by reaſon of your greatneſſe. When <hi>Marcus Curio</hi> was told, if he would pleaſe <hi>Dyoniſius,</hi> he needed not feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on turnips; he anſwered him that told him ſo, If he could but bring himſelfe to feed upon turnips, he need not pleaſe <hi>Dyoniſius.</hi> What is the reaſon that ſo many of the Nobility have betrayed their truſt, have debaſed themſelves, have brought a ſtaine upon their families, but becauſe they could not tell how to be low? They were afraid of loſſe of honour, or eſtate, they dared not truſt God with them. If ſome of you could have truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God with your Honours, you might have been the moſt honourable Noblemen in Chriſtendome. He that knowes how to be abaſed, will know better how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, which is the ſecond Leſſon, <hi>I know how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I could tel this Congregation how every one might get abundance, I beleeve I ſhould have an attentive Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory if it were till midnight; but I am now to ſhew you how you ſhould ſanctifie Gods name in your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, Theſe are times of want, rather then of abounding.</p>
            <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> if indeed I ſhould now preach this point in ſome places of England, it would be a very unſeaſonable argument unto them; but among us, there are ſome who doe now more abound then ever they did in their lives; ſome who lived meanly enough before theſe times, yet now they can live bravely, who have raiſed their eſtates out of the miſery of the times. Certainly it will never be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113318:11"/> any honour to a man and his poſterity, if hereafter it ſhall be found that he hath grown rich by the evill of the times. That which is reported of Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> who was Lord Chancellour of England many yeares, was much to his honour, that when he dyed, he left his ſonne not above 25. l. <hi>per annum</hi> more then the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance his father left him. It will be to the honour of men to be found rather poorer then richer in after times. But though you have not that abundance that you have had, yet in reſpect of thouſands, yea millions of your brethren, ye doe now abound. You think perhaps that except you have many thouſands comming in, you are in want. Some of you are it may be of the judgement of <hi>Marcus Craſſus,</hi> whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks of, who accounted no man rich, except he could of his owne charges main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an Armie. It may be you have not enough to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your phanſies, yet you have enough to ſupply your wants, and over. I am ſure you abound more then <hi>Paul</hi> did, yet he ſaith in this Chapter, ver. 18. <hi>I have all, and abound, I am full.</hi> Oh that you would but give your hearts to learne how to abound in what you have. It is a good ſigne of grace to be more ſolicitous to know how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, then to get abundance; to be more carefull to uſe what you have for God, then to maintaine it for your ſelves. Therefore the argument being of that great neceſſity and uſe, as I hope I ſhall make it appeare to you before I have done, I ſhall enlarge my ſelfe in it, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it into theſe ſeven Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall ſhew, firſt, When a man may be ſaid to abound.</item>
               <item>2. The difficulty of this Leſſon.</item>
               <item>3. The neceſſity of it.</item>
               <item>4. The myſterie of godlineſſe that is in it.</item>
               <item>5. The excellency of it.</item>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113318:11"/>
               <item>6. The ſeverall leſſons that are to be learned, to make a man skilfull in it.</item>
               <item>7. The Application of all.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the firſt. When may a man be ſaid to know how to abound?</head>
               <p>When he can ſet a due value and price upon the good things he enjoyes, ſo as neither to prize them too low nor too high. Honours and riches are in themſelves the good bleſſings of God, they come out of Gods good treaſure. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.12. <hi>The Lord will open to thee his good treaſure.</hi> And if you be godly, they are unto you the fruit of the Promiſe, they are given to you as encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements in the wayes of God, as good utenſils for Gods ſervice, giving you larger opportunities for the work of the Lord, then thoſe have who are poore. I beſeech you, Right Honourable, conſider of this one note, it is an excellent argument of truth of grace, yea and of a good meaſure of grace, to account the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of honours and riches to conſiſt in this, that they give larger opportunities for the ſervice of God, then others have, who are in a lower condition; to make the eſtimate of your honours and eſtates, by the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of your ſervice. A poore man may be as precious to God as you, but he can doe but little for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not thoſe outward helps that ye have. You enjoy great mercies, but wherein lyes the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of them? can you ſay as in the preſence of God, I bleſſe God for theſe outward mercies I have, but that which enlarges my heart moſt in bleſſing his Name for them, is the large opportunities they afford me to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Name, which otherwiſe I ſhould not have? Many great men make the eſtimate of their honours and eſtates to be this, they have more ability and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113318:12"/> by them to ſatisfie their luſts without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll, which others have not.</p>
               <p>They are the good bleſſings of God, but they are but common bleſſings; the enjoying of them makes not a man the better by them; as the letter in a word that hath a flouriſh about it, puts not more to the ſenſe of the word then another doth. Theſe things make no man more acceptable to God, they are no ſignes of a good condition, more then a painted face is a ſigne of a good complexion. You would be loth to chooſe a wife by the painting of her face; it would be your folly to judge of her complexion according to her paint. Certainly it is as good an argument to prove the goodneſſe of the conſtitution of her body, as honours and riches are to prove the good condition of any man before God. Theſe things are bleſſings, but they are bleſſings of the left hand, they are outward bleſſings; if they be good to you, it muſt be from ſome goodneſſe in you, to uſe them for good; as a mans cloathes firſt warmed by the heat of the body, and then they heat, they are good things; but mans happineſſe is not in the having them, nor his miſery in the want of them, they make no great difference in mens eſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, when a man knowes how to proportion the uſe of what he enjoyes, ſo much to ſuch an uſe, and at ſuch a time, and no more. You muſt not think be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what you have is your own, &amp; you have enough, therefore you need not regard to keep meaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in the uſe of it. When <hi>Zeno</hi> the Philoſopher re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved one for immoderate feaſting, he anſwered, He ſpent of his owne, and he had enough: <hi>Zeno</hi> replyed, If your Cook ſhould put two or three handfuls of ſalt into your meat more then was fit, and ſhould ſay, He
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113318:12"/> had ſalt enough by him that coſt nothing; would this be a good anſwer? So for the time of the enjoying of your abundance, you muſt know your ſeaſon, there is a time to mourne as well as to rejoyce; at ſome times you may take a more free uſe of the creature, at other times you muſt deny your ſelves. It was a great charge of God upon thoſe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 22.12, 13. <hi>when God called to weeping and to mourning, there was joy and gladneſſe, eating fleſh and drinking wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, when a man can ſo uſe his abundance, as to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> avoid the temptations that goe along with it, he is a wiſe man that can doe ſo. If you give children fiſh with many ſmall bones, they know not how to eat the fiſh without choaking themſelves. In proſperity there are many ſmall bones, there is much danger, it requires much wiſdome to take the good, and avoid the evill: God doth not require you to caſt away your abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that you might avoid the danger that is in it, as <hi>Crates, Ariſtippus,</hi> and other Philoſophers did fooliſhly. It is weakneſſe to have need to deny ones ſelfe the uſe of the creature, becauſe of the danger in it; but yet he had need to be very vigilant in obſerving the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it, that he may avoid it. You greedily many times ſwallow in the ſweetneſſe of your abundance, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what poyſon of temptation may lye in it, and ſo ſwallowing downe all, you are undone by it. <hi>The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of fooles deſtroyes them,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ei conciliandae pacis &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae cum Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thero idem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidiſſe, quod illis qui prae nimia avidita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te etiam faeces haurirent.</note>) It was ſaid of <hi>Bucer,</hi> that he was ſo eager of peace with <hi>Luther,</hi> that he was like to a man that through much greedineſſe takes in dregs and all. The fooliſh hearts of men are ſo taken with the ſweet of their proſperity, that they ſcarce have a ſerious thought of any danger in it, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, then a man knowes how to abound, when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113318:13"/> he can have command over his ſpirit in the uſe of what he enjoyes; when a man can ſo take pleaſure, that his pleaſure takes not him: you ſay of ſuch men, that they have great poſſeſſions, but their poſſeſſions rather have them. It is ſordidneſſe in a man to be a ſervant to his ſervant. It was the curſe of <hi>Cain, A ſervant of ſervants ſhalt thou be.</hi> Thus when a man hath no command over his ſpirit, but is a ſervant to what he hath, the curſe of <hi>Cain</hi> is upon him. When you cannot be merry in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, nor in the liberall uſe of the creatures, but by them are made unfit for holy duties, you now are brought under the power of them, you doe not enjoy them. How ſeldome have you been able to let out your hearts to mirth, jollity, and contentment to the fleſh, ſo as you could at the evening freely poure them forth before God in Prayer? No, many times it is a day or two before you can get any command over your ſpirits again. Certainly you have not learned how to abound.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, then doth a man know how to abound, when he ſo enjoyes what he hath, as he is ready to part with it for God. They who have lived at a high rate all their dayes, now cannot live low; they will rather venture to break their conſciences, or doe any thing, rather then to be meane. But when a man can ſay, Lord, if thou haſt any other way to honour thy Name by me, then in the enjoyment of what I have, here I am, doe with me as thou pleaſeſt: and when God takes away his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts from him, can ſay, <hi>The Lord giveth, the Lord taketh, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord;</hi> this man hath learned how to abound: but when mens hearts cannot enjoy theſe comforts, but they ſo cleave to them, that they cannot part with them without the rending of their hearts, if they loſe a little of what they have, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113318:13"/> cry out, They are undone; theſe men never knew how to abound.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, when men know how to enjoy God in their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> abundance, and to be led to him by it, they are not crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts that ſatisfie them, but God in them; the creature is but the channell that lets God into their hearts. <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.3. <hi>The whole earth is full of thy glory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plenitudo toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us terrae gloria ejus.</note> ſo you have it in your books, but it is more proper to read it thus, <hi>His glory is the fulneſſe of the earth.</hi> When a man can ſay, It is the glory of God that is the fulneſſe of my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and my eſtate, and of my comforts, it is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God that I enjoy in theſe, that rejoyceth my ſoule: it is true, the Ordinances are the ſpeciall chanels that let out Gods goodneſſe to me; yet that ſweetneſſe of his love, that communion which I have with him in theſe outward things, are more to me then all the world; this man hath learned how to abound. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>The peace of God ſhall keep their hearts;</hi> but <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>The God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> It is not enough to a gracious heart to have the peace of God, but he muſt have the God of peace; ſo it is not enough for him to have honour from God, but he muſt have the God of that honour; all the riches in the world cannot ſatisfie him, except he hath the God that gave him thoſe riches. When thy heart can be carryed quickly through the creatures, to enjoy God as the fulneſſe of what thou haſt; and when the creature is made uſe of, to draw forth the graces of the Spirit of God in thee; ſo that the more thou doſt abound, the more are thy graces acted to God the fountaine of all, now thou haſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how to abound: but where is the man who doth enjoy more of God in abundance then in want?</p>
               <p>Seventhly, then hath a man learned how to abound, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> when he hath learned how to trade with his abundance;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113318:14"/> not how to keep it to himſelfe, but how to improve it for God, and the Publique, and the reliefe of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, according to what he is able, when he improves his honour to lift up Gods honour on high, &amp; his riches, by being rich in good works, when he accounts himſelf a ſteward, and all he hath to be as talents given him to trade with, not for himſelfe, but for his Maſter.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. When ſome afflictions that you meet withall in your proſperity, are not hinderances to the comfortable enjoyment of the mercies you have. Many men have ſuch weak ſpirits, that though God gives them abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of mercies, yet if they have but any one affliction befall them, in the midſt of all their abundance they forget all their mercies, God hath no thankfulneſſe from them for them all; one affliction is as the grave to bury hundreds of mercies. Surely <hi>Haman</hi> knew not how to abound, when he was but croſt in the want of having the bowing of <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s knee; all the honour he had in the Court was nothing to him. So it was with <hi>Ahab,</hi> one would think he had enough to have ſatisfied one man, being ſo great a King; yet becauſe he had not <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, he is ſick, and will not eate. A ſmall thing laid upon a mans eye, will keep the ſight of all the heavens from him; ſo many times a little affliction keeps the ſight of abundance of mercies, yea heavenly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from you. Surely you have not learned how to abound.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. Then a man knowes how to abound, when in his abundance he knowes himſelfe; few men know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they are raiſed by proſperity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.20. <hi>Put them in feare Oh Lord, that they may know themſelves to be but men.</hi> When men are got above their brethren, their hearts begin to ſwell, as if they were not men, as if all the world were made onely to give them content.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113318:14"/> Right Honourable, while I am mentioning of theſe things, ſee what cauſe you have to be humbled, to fall downe before the Lord this day; you have enjoyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, but either you have not been in the ſchoole of Chriſt, or you have been but ill proficients in it. How few of you have learned thus to abound? Let this be the matter of your humiliation in the dayes of your Faſting. Some of you are cut ſhort of your former abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, God calls you now to be humbled for your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>The difficulty of this leſſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Men think it is hard to be brought down under afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but verily to know how to abound is much harder. You who live in this place, think your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions to be far better then of thoſe who live under the rage of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; you yet enjoy ſo much, as if you be not unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, you muſt needs acknowledge, that in compariſon of them, you abound in mercies. You think their leſſon, how to beare patiently ſuch great afflictions as are upon them; is very hard; but the truth is, of both, you have the hardeſt leſſon to learne. It is harder to know how to abound, then to know how to want. This may ſeem a paradox; but before we have done, I hope I ſhall make the truth of it out fully to you.</p>
               <p>Mariners uſe to ſay, if they have ſea-roome enough, they care not; but your greateſt danger is in your ſea-roome. It is a ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and a very true one,<note place="margin">Difficilius eſt pugnare cum libidine, quam cum cruce. <hi>Aug</hi> Omne malum facilius vinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas. <hi>Cypr.</hi>
                  </note> It is a harder thing to fight with a mans luſts, then to fight with the croſſe: And of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> There is no evill but is eaſier overcome then pleaſure. There is more skill required to manage an Eaſt-Indie Ship, then a Boat in the Thames. The warme beames of the Sunne gets the Travellers cloak ſooner from him, then the wind and ſtormes can doe. Many who fled for Religion in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113318:15"/> Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, knew how to want; but comming againe in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, enjoying proſperity, they knew not how to abound, they proved naught. Manna could endure the heat of the fire, for the people baked it;<note place="margin">Eliſaeus cum magno honore &amp; ſaeculi dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae donum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit; Elias pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugus &amp; perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus. <hi>Aug. de Mirab. l. 2. c. 26.</hi>
                  </note> but it melted before the heat of the Sunne. Many have been melted by the heat of proſperity, who ſtood it out againſt the ſcorching heat of affliction. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> prayed for a double ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> to be upon him; and why ſo? <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives a reaſon, <hi>Elijah</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, baniſhed, lived in the wilderneſſe; but <hi>Eliſha</hi> was to live at Court, and therefore he had need of a double ſpirit, that he might know how to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, there are more duties required of men who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, then of thoſe who want. A poore man who works hard for his living all day, what hath he to doe, but in the morning to commend himſelf and his family to God, and ſo goe forth to his labour? but you who abound, have a great deale of work to doe, the great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes that concern the publique good of State and Church lye heavy upon your ſhoulders. Some think when they have great eſtates, they may live idly, that they have nothing to doe but to ſpend their dayes in mirth and jollity; but certainly there are no men in the world who have greater work to doe then Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, Lords, and ſuch as are in place of dignity and power.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there is a greater variety of temptations in abundance, then in want. It is true, Poverty is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its temptations, but Proſperity hath farre more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it. Flyes come thickeſt to ſweet things; ſo <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> which ſignifies the god of flies, the prince of devils, loves moſt to be amongſt men who doe moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound. Rats and Mice come to full barnes, rather then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113318:15"/> to empty places; ſo the vermine of temptations doe more haunt abundance then want. We reade of <hi>Joſephs</hi> portion, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.13. <hi>Bleſſed of the Lord be his land, for the precious things of heaven, for the dew, and for the deep, and for the precious fruits brought forth by the ſunne, and for the precious things put forth by the moone, and for the chiefe things of the ancient mountains, and for the precious things of the laſting hills, and for the precious things of the earth, and fulneſſe thereof.</hi> Thus we finde <hi>Joſeph</hi> was very rich, but we reade of no Tribe that was to ſuffer ſo much oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the Tribe of <hi>Joſeph. Gen.</hi> 49.22. <hi>Joſeph is a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bough, even a fruitfull bough by a well, whoſe branches run over the wall. The archers have ſorely grieved him, and ſhot at him, and hated him.</hi> None of the Patriarchs did ſo much abound as <hi>Joſeph;</hi> none were ſo ſorely ſhot at and hated as he was. Travailers fling not at a tree that is empty, but at ſuch as is full of fruit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the temptations of thoſe who abound, are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> more ſutable then the temptations of ſuch as ſuffer want. There is a tediouſneſſe in the temptations that thoſe which are in afflictions meet with, they are tempted to impatience, and deſpaire, and ſhifting courſes; theſe are tedious even to nature: but the temptations in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance are to ſatisfie our luſt, to have our will. Lay rats bane in the window, and the child is in greater danger, then if poyſon were mixed in Aloes.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Temptations in abundance are more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> they inſinuate into the ſoule, and bring in much evil by things lawfull. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.19. the temptations that come by riches are called <hi>the deceitfulneſſe of riches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, But above all it is difficult to learn how to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> abound, becauſe proſperity affords ſo much food and fuell to mens luſts, by which they are heated, pampered, and ſo grow ſtrong. You will not ſet a child upon a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113318:16"/> luſty pampered horſe.<note place="margin">Difficile eſt eſſe in honore, fine tumore. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note> The luſt of pride, how is it fed by honours and riches, and what more unruly in the heart, then pride fed to the full? whereas in afflictions, the pride of men is almoſt ſtarved. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.6. <hi>They were filled, their heart was exalted, they have forgotten me.</hi> So un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, men who have eſtates have fuell for that luſt, and thoſe who are above others, whom none dare meddle with, can ſatisfie it without controll, this they account the bravery of their lives. The like may be ſaid of Malice and Revenge.</p>
               <p>The Scripture gives us many evidences of this, that it is harder to know how to abound, then how to want: As,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the frequent and ſolemne charges of God to thoſe that abound, to take heed to themſelves, more then to thoſe that want. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11, 12. <hi>When thou ſhalt have eaten, and art full, then beware leſt thou forget the Lord.</hi> Oh would to God this Scripture were writ over your full table. And Chap. 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>leſt when thou haſt eaten and art full, and haſt built goodly houſes, and dwelt therein, &amp;c. Then thy heart be lifted up and thou forget the Lord thy God.</hi> As if God ſhould ſay, I am not ſo ſolicitous about you when you are in the wilderneſſe, you will not ſo eaſily forget me when you are there, but when you are come to your houſes, when your herds, your flocks, ſilver and gold are multiplyed, oh then beware that you forget not the Lord. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15, 16. <hi>That thou maiſt gather in thy corne, thy wine, and thine oyle, that thou maiſt eate and be full, take heed to your ſelves that your hearts be not deceived.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Virtus fidei pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculis ſecura, ſecuritate peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitatur.</note> It is a good ſpeech of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of faith in dangers is ſecure, and in ſecurity it is in danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we never reade that ever a full or proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate was ſo much as the occaſion of the converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113318:16"/> of any to God: but we finde in Scripture that an afflicted eſtate hath been bleſt to many for this end, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Job</hi> 33.14.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, few of Gods children have been the worſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for afflictions, but almoſt all of them, whom we read of in Scripture to have been in a proſperous eſtate, have been the worſe for it. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.3. it is ſaid, <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat walked in the firſt wayes of David. Davids</hi> firſt wayes were in his afflicted eſtate, and they were the beſt; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdome, you ſee how fouly he fell by his proſperity.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it hath been the way of God conſtantly to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> keep his people downe in a low eſtate, eſpecially in the times of the Goſpell. This holds forth to all the world, that it is a hard thing to know how to abound: for it the Saints were able to manage abundance as well as want, they ſhould have it, in time of ſo great mercy, for they are heyres of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>The neceſsity of this leſſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>But though the leſſon be very hard, yet it is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if you abound, and know not how to abound, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> you will have many creatures which you have uſe of continually crying to God againſt you, for the bondage you bring them under. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.22. who are they that doe moſt keepe the creatures in bondage, but thoſe who have the moſt plentifull uſe of them, and ſubject them to their luſts? Theſe creatures cry, Oh Lord, we were made for thee, and we would be working for thee, who art the chiefe good, and the higheſt end; but here is a man that hath us at his command, and he forceth us to that which is contrary to our nature: This cry of the creatures is very ſad againſt thee who doſt abuſe them; they were never made to be ſerviceable to thy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113318:17"/> luſts; thou art an oppreſſor of the whole Creation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, you who abound, and know not how to abound, you ſinne againſt much mercy. The abuſe of mercy is the greateſt aggravation of a mans ſinne. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Doe you thus requite the Lord?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.8. It is miſerable, when there ſhall be no other uſe of mercy, but to aggravate thy ſinne. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.25, 26. <hi>They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted themſelves in thy great goodneſſe. Nevertheleſſe they were diſobedient, and rebelled againſt thee, and caſt thy law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their back.</hi> This <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> is very dreadfull; ſuch a man is raiſed to a high eſtate and honour, <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> he is a ſwearer, <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> he is uncleane, his family is prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, if you know not how to abound, you will grow extreame wicked. <hi>Job</hi> 21.13, 14, 15. <hi>They ſpend their dayes in wealth, therefore they ſay unto God, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes. What is the Almighty, that we ſhould ſerve him? Jer.</hi> 2.7, 8. <hi>Their land is full of ſilver and gold,</hi> it followes, <hi>their land alſo is full of Idols.</hi> It may be thus ſaid of many Families, They are full of riches, of the good bleſſings of God, and they are alſo as full of ſinne. What is the greatnes of many mens ſpirits, but this, that they dare boldly ſin againſt the God of heaven? they account it their excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency to goe beyond others in wickedneſſe, they glory in their ſhame, like thoſe Nobles I have read of in the Iſle of <hi>Samobarre</hi> in the Eaſt-Indies, who ſtigmatized themſelves with a hot iron, in token of honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, if you learn not how to abound, you are the men who have your portion in this world, like thoſe <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.14. I have read of <hi>Gregorie,</hi> when he was advanced to high preferment, profeſt no Scripture was ever ſo terrible in his eares, as that, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.24. <hi>Ye have received your conſolation;</hi> it ſounded in his eares as <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaid
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113318:17"/> that Scripture, <hi>Ariſe ye dead and come to judgement,</hi> ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his. If God ſhould ſay to any of you, You ſhall have all your eſtares as full as ever, yea with a hundred fold increaſe, but that ſhal be your portion, all the good that ever you are like to have from me, there would be cauſe for you to wring your handss, to fall down upon your faces in the anguiſh of your ſoules, to cry and howl at the hearing of ſuch a doom as this. For though it is true in regard of your ſinfulneſſe you ſhould judge your ſelves unworthy of the leaſt crumme of bread, yet woe unto you that ever you were borne, if your portion ſhould be the enjoyment of the whole world; you had need then learn how to abound; for if you doe not, God thereby doth manifeſt that he hath ſeparated you to this doome, to give you no other portion but what you have here.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, you had need learn how to abound, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> there goes along with your abundance a ſecret curſe of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.22, 23. <hi>Let their table be made a ſnare to them, and that which ſhould have been for their welfare, let it become a trap;</hi> but few underſtand this: it is their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yea a part of the curſe that is upon them, for ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>Let their eyes be darkned that they ſee not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, you had need learne how to abound; for il <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> you doe not, you will do abundance of hurt in the places where you live. A man who abounds, and hath not grace with his abundance, is a publique evill to the Countrie where he lives. Thoſe who are meane poore people, though they be wicked, yet they can doe no great hurt; but a man who is in honour and eſteeme in the world, and hath a great eſtate, if he be not godly, he is very miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous. A little weed in a garden is not very hurtfull; but if there growes a great Elder-tree in the midſt of it, it ſpoils all about it.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113318:18"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, your abundance will endanger your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation if you learn not how to abound. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hebrewes ſaith, he wonders how any Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour can be ſaved; and our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.24. ſaith, <hi>It is eaſier for a Camell to goe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly, if you learn not this leſſon, if ever you bee brought into afflictions, oh how grievous will they be! your abundance will prepare matter for the terrours of your conſciences, yea it will make death very terrible, when you ſhall look back and conſider how much you have had from God, and how little you have done for him; yea, how much ye have done againſt him: death will ſtrain out the ſweet, but leave the guilt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4. <hi>The myſterie of godlineſſe there is in learning how to abound.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I am inſtructed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſtrength of reaſon may goe farre in ordering a proſperous condition ſo as not to be very offenſive, but there is a great myſtery of godlineſſe in knowing how to abound in a chriſtian ſpirituall way.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A godly man learnes to abound by being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.20. <hi>A faithfull man ſhall abound with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</hi> Many think the only way to get abundance is by being falſe, by ſhifting courſes; they dare not truſt to the wayes of faithfulneſſe, they ſee a mighty Current of oppoſition againſt them, but the godly man deſires neither to get nor to enjoy more in the world, then he may have by being faithfull.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He learnes to abound by often reſigning up all his abundance to God, not by keeping it to his own proper advantage; Lord I profeſſe all to be thine, to enjoy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in order to thee; take all, improve all, lay out all for the praiſe of thine own name; by this he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes his abundance with more comfort and freedome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113318:18"/> of ſpirit. The oftner any thng is given up into Gods hands, and comes out of them to us, the better it is; thoſe men who having got any thing out of Gods hands once, dare not venture to put it into them again, enjoy not the comfort and bleſſing of what they have; that man who can dayly as freely and cheerfully reſign what he hath to God, as receive any thing from him, is the only man that is bleſſed in what he enjoies in this world.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſeeks to preſerve his eſtate, and to enrich him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by communicating what he hath to the neceſſities of others, and the publick. This is a myſterie to the world. <hi>Iſay</hi> 32.8. <hi>The liberall man deviſeth liberall things:</hi> and what then? ſo he may loſe all he hath? No, <hi>by liberall things he ſhall ſtand.</hi> He thinks it more gain to part with any thing to doe good by, then to keep it for himſelfe. 1 <hi>Tim. v.</hi> 17. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world that they be not high minded, that they truſt not in uncertain riches, but that they be rich in good works.</hi> Here is a way of being rich that the world is not acquainted with, by being rich in good works; the more he layes out in good works, the richer he is. God himſelfe accounts his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be in the works of mercy, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>That he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace, in his kindneſſe towards us.</hi> The Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8. brings this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to move men to communicate their eſtates for the good of others; <hi>God is able to make all grace abound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that yee alwayes having all ſufficiency in all things, may abound to every good work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. He learns how to abound by moderating his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in his abundance, by the moderation of his joy he increaſeth his joy, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Rejoyce, and again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce.</hi> This is a good exhortation. Well then, let us let out our hearts to the uttermoſt in joy: nay, ſaith the Apoſtle, you muſt take care you keep your affections
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113318:19"/> within bounds. <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men.</hi> You will have more ſolid comfort in the moderation of your affections, then others ſhall have in the greateſt liberty they take to give up themſelves to mirth and jollity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By his abundance, his humility is increaſed; to be humble in the enjoyment of abundance is much, but to be humbled by it is a myſtery. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18. The Lord having ſpoken of great riches and honour he beſtowed upon <hi>David,</hi> and would ſtill further beſtow upon him; he tels him his houſe ſhould be great among the great men of the earth; was <hi>Davids</hi> heart puffed up by this? No; <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>went King</hi> David, <hi>and ſate before the Lord, and what is my houſe that thou haſt brought me hitherto? wherefore thou art great oh God. Saul</hi> was little in his own eyes, before God made him great: But when he was made great, God was leſſe eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him. The greater <hi>David</hi> was, the leſſe he was in his own eyes, and the greater was God in them; not, Lord I am a happy man, that I am made ſo great; but who am I, and what is my houſe? but thou art great oh Lord.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Though he judges himſelfe unworthy of the leaſt good he hath, yet his heart is raiſed in a holy manner above all his abundance; at the ſame time hee judges himſelfe unworthy of the leaſt crumme, and yet he thinks all creatures in heaven and earth too low for him to be his portion, this is a myſterie. No man knowes in a ſpirituall way how to abound,<note place="margin">Sive vivimus, ſive morimur, Domini ſumus; non tantum Genitivo caſu, ſed Nominat. plur. vitae &amp; morti domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</note> but he who is above all his abundance. <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaking of that place, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee live, or whether wee dye, wee are the Lords:</hi> This, ſaith he, is not only to be underſtood in the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive caſe ſingular, <hi>Domini;</hi> but in the nominative plural: we are <hi>Domini,</hi> the Lords of life and death, whether
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113318:19"/> we dye or live; though wee be not Lords of ſo much Land, of ſuch Mannors; we cannot Lord it over ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Tenants, yet over life and death we are Lords; we can Lord it over them. Death takes away all your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and Lordſhips from you, but death is part of the poſſeſſions of the Saints, they are Lords over it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours.</hi> A gracious heart who lies low under God and Chriſt, yet hath all other things under his feet; yea, the lower he lies, the more hath he; all the bravery, pomp, and glory of the world, under his feet: great is this myſterie of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. According to the increaſe of his abundance, he ſeeks a proportionable meaſure of holineſſe. <hi>Solomon</hi> deſired much wiſdome, becauſe he had a great peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to govern; men who have ſenſuall hearts, think a little Religion is enough for a Gentleman or Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; it is for poore men who have little elſe to minde or content themſelves in, to look after Religion in the ſtrictneſſe of it. But if God gives a gracious man abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, he doth not think that meaſure of grace that he had before, will ſerve his turne now, except God cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his grace to abound as wel as his eſtate and honour, he lookes upon himſelfe as miſerable.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He is as much apprehenſive and ſenſible of his dependance upon God in the height of proſperitie, as in the depth of adverſitie. Hence Noblemen and Princes are taught by Chriſt to come every day to Gods gate to beg their bread.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A godly man enjoyes his abundance aright by getting all he hath ſanctified to him by the Word and Prayer. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4, 5. All a man hath is ſanctified when it is conſecrated to the laſt end, for God, and for the furtherance of eternall good; as time and place
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113318:20"/> is ſanctified when there is a conſecration upon them for God; ſo when the bleſſing of God is upon my eſtate, all I have, ſo as all works to my eternall good in the glory of God, now it is ſanctified to me.</p>
               <p>But how comes it to be ſo?</p>
               <p>By the Word and Prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Through the Word of the Goſpel, revealing the reſtitution of my right, forfeited by ſinne, yea a higher title then ever I had in <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By the Word of Promiſe, which gives nothing without a bleſſing to it. If indeed I had what I enjoy meerly in a naturall way of general providence, I could not expect ſuch a bleſſing; but now enjoying all by the Word, I enjoy it all in a ſpirituall way, all is ſanctified to me. Hence of all men, Gentlemen and Noblemen have moſt cauſe to be much converſant in Scripture; it would be a ſad charge upon any of you, who abound ſo much in the world, that you have not a Bible in your cloſets, or ſeldome look into it.</p>
               <p>And by Prayer. The more any man hath, the more he had need to pray. Carnall men will pray much in affliction, but to be put on to prayer by proſperity, this is rare. Gentlemen had need pray more then poore men, Noblemen more then Gentlemen. But if this be a truth, certainly it is a myſterie; few of you think ſo, fewer doe ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. <hi>The excellency of this leſſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. When this is learned, grace in you will be very conſpicuous; it will appeare in the luſtre of it as a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond in a golden ring,<note place="margin">Magna faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſt, à faeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate non vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> or rather ſet in a Crowne, ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, and is more glorious then in a dirty rag. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.16. there is a Propheſie that the Saints ſhall be as the ſtones of a Crowne lifted up; it is in part made good, when grace appears in the glory of it in you who are in eminent place.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113318:20"/>
               <p n="2">2. You may doe abundance of good: many ſoules will bleſſe God for you, and for all the abundance you enjoy, of which there is ſo good an improvement. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God that ever ſuch men lived in ſuch places and times; the Cauſe of God, and the good of his Saints, how hath it been promoted by them! will not this be a greater good to you, then all your titles of honour, and bravery of your lives? <hi>Judges</hi> 5.9. <hi>My heart is towards the governours of the people which offer themſelves willingly: Bleſſe ye the Lord.</hi> Becauſe of the great ſervice that a rich man may doe, <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo moved, when he had liked to have loſt <hi>Sergius Paulus,</hi> the Deputy of the country, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.7, 8. &amp;c. he ſet his eyes upon <hi>Elimas,</hi> who ſought to turne him away from the faith, which he began to hearken after and embrace, and ſaid, <hi>Oh full of all ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and all miſchief, thou child of the devil, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This argues much ſtrength of grace,<note place="margin">Magni pectoris inter ſecunda moderatio. <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </note> as the braines reſiſting abundance of vapours, ſo as not to be hurt by them, argues the ſtrength of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From theſe who have learned thus, God receives moſt of that rent of praiſe and honour that is due to him for all the good things of the earth, he lets out to the children of men. You who are great Landlords, complaine much that in theſe times you cannot receive your rents, they were never ſo ill paid as they are now: call your ſelves to account, how well you pay your rents to the Lord, of whom you hold all you have. You eſteeme well of ſuch as are certaine and punctuall in paying your rents, God eſteemes high of thoſe who render to him in a conſtant way his rent for thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plentifull enjoyments they have in this world.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There is no fear that adverſity, that any afflictions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113318:21"/> ſhould doe hurt to ſuch who know thus how to uſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. If you can deliver your ſelves from the deceits of the one, it will not be very difficult to reſiſt the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of the other. <hi>Nulla infaelicitas frangit, quem nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la faelicitas corrumpit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. This is the more excellent, becauſe it is ſo rare. Where is the man who is able to ſtand againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a proſperous eſtate? if Adverſity hath ſlaine her thouſands, Proſperity hath ſlain her ten thouſands. <hi>Rara virtus humilitas honorata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. How ſweetly and comfortably may ſuch dye, who have honoured God with their riches and honours? They may with a holy boldneſſe in the cloſe of all, look up to God, and ſay with <hi>Nehemiah, Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ. laſt, Remember me oh my God for good.</hi> Let God be remembred with your goods, and he will remember you for good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>6. <hi>He that will be skilfull in this myſterie of knowing how to abound, muſt learne alſo theſe leſſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The leſſon of the feare of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11, 12. God forewarnes his people that they ſhould not forget him, when they enjoyed abundance of all good things. <hi>Ver.</hi> 13. he addes as a meanes thereunto, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, and ſerve him.</hi> You muſt not preſume to doe what you liſt; let the feare of God be upon you to keep you from pride, wantonneſſe, and licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. We reade of <hi>Nehemiah, Chap.</hi> 5. though he were in honour, and had much power in his hands to ſatisfie his will upon men as others did, they made their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants rule over the people, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>but ſo did not I,</hi> ſayes he, why? <hi>becauſe of the feare of God.</hi> My Lords, God hath raiſed you high above others, much power is in your hands, take heed of abuſing it to oppreſſion. If your ſpirits be too generous and noble to oppreſſe any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113318:21"/> your ſelves take heed that your ſervants be not made to rule with rigour over the people. That great out-cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Committees for rigorous oppreſſing, partiall wayes, and againſt ſome of your ſervants for exacting extreame fees, comes not it may be ſo high as to your eares; of all oppreſſions, the oppreſſions by ſervants, by men of meane quality, is the worſt. Oh that you all could ſay, If others doe thus, as for us we doe not ſo, becauſe of the feare of God; whatſoever other Lords have done, doe, or ſhall doe, in the abuſe of their power, and the great truſt committed to them, God forbid we ſhould doe ſo, for the feare of God is upon us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Learne the leſſon of the different principles from whence creature comforts come, ſometimes from Love, ſometimes from Anger and hatred;<note place="margin">Admone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ſunt qui hoc mundo proſperantur, ut ſolerter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderent praeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti vitae proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, aliquando datur ut ad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem vitam provocet, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando ut in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum plenius damnet. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note> the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, would cauſe you to be unſatisfied in all your abundance, till you know from what principle it flowes. The very ſearching for ſatisfaction in this, would have great power upon your ſpirits, to order and regulate them in the enjoyment of your abundance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Learne the leſſon of your own unworthineſſe, why ſhould God give you rather then others? who hath made you to differ?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Learne that all you have are talents that your great Lord hath betruſted you with to trade for him; you are but Stewards of what you have; you are to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all; you had need then keep your books even. How can you give account of your mercies, when you cannor count them?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Learne that man is borne to labour, yea the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt upon the earth not exempted; none of you are born to live like the Leviathan. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.26. <hi>There is the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan, whom hou haſt made to play in the ſea.</hi> You came not into the world, your lives are not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113318:22"/> for this end; there are other labours in the world beſides ſervile, that God hath fitted for the moſt noble ſpirits.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Learne the excellency of ſpirituall riches, of true riches; the leaſt degree of grace, yea every gracious work is more worth then heaven and earth, ſayes <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> He profeſſed he preferred the underſtanding of one of the Pſalmes, above all the riches of the world. If we were got up to heaven, the earth would ſeeme as little to us, as now we being upon the earth, the ſtarres ſeeme to be.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Learne that the leaſt ſinne is a greater evill, then all earthly proſperity can be good. When you commit any one ſinne, in that you are more miſerable, then you can be happy in all your honours &amp; eſtates. If you were throughly inſtructed in this, then 1. you would take heed of getting or preferring riches or honours by any way of ſinne. <hi>Abraham</hi> would not have it ſaid, that the King of Sodome made him rich: let it never be ſaid that ſinne hath made me rich, or preſerved me being ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you had learned this, whatſoever you have or ſhall get by ſinne, you will certainly reſtore to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of your power.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This would make you take heed of the abuſe of what you have to ſinne: for it tells you you ſhall doe your ſelves more hurt by any ſinne, then all you have in the world can doe you good.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Learne, this time of your life is the time that God hath ſet to provide for eternity. This would make you ſerious, and ſee need ſo to be; it would take off much of the vanity and jollity of your ſpirits, whereas now eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought that does but tend to any ſeriouſneſſe, you think is melancholy. This would make you take heed how you ſpend ſo much time in the enjoyment of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113318:22"/> things of this world, or make any uſe of them, that might be the leaſt hinderance to you in that great work you live for, this would cauſe you to improve all you have to the uttermoſt, for the furtherance of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and your owne ſpirituall good. In doing thus, you will learne how to abound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, you ſee of what great uſe Religion is to great men. You who are Noblemen and Gentlemen, who have great eſtates to leave to your children, are not your deſires and endeavours that they may have bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſutable to your eſtates you intend to leave them? how vile a thing is it in the eyes of all men, for one to have a great eſtate, but no breeding! he is a foole, he knowes not how to manage his eſtate now hee hath it, he will quickly embezell it away, and undoe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Why ſhould you not then account it a great evill for your ſelves or children, to have honours and eſtates, but no skill to know how to uſe them for God, and the furtherance of your or their eternall good? It is onely godlineſſe learned in the ſchoole of Chriſt teacheth this. This is the moſt neceſſary, the moſt honourable bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Breed up your young heyres, and the reſt of your children, in the knowledge, and as much as in you lies, in the love of godlineſſe, that when they come to enjoy thoſe faire eſtates they ſucceed you in, they may be eminent for the honour of God, and the good of their Countrey, in their generation. Be in love with godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ye rich men, and eſpecially the Nobles of our Land; how happy were we if there were a hopefull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113318:23"/> of Nobility and Gentry! our ſufferings are from the diſaffection ſo many of theſe have had to Religion; I hope there is yet a time when god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe ſhall bee honoured upon the earth by great ones. Seek for grace for your ſelves and poſterity; God hath given you plenty of the lower ſprings, ſeek the upper.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2. Thoſe are rebuked who onely take care to get abundance, but are not at all ſolicitous to learne how to abound. <hi>Jude</hi> 12. this among other characters is given of a wicked man, that <hi>he eates without feare,</hi> he takes in freely the delight of the creature; but there is no feare leſt God ſhould not have that glory that is due to him from it, this he mindes not at all; we have not hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learned how to abound, Let us juſtifie God in cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us ſhort now of what formerly we had; the abuſe of abounding that was formerly, was moſt dreadfull; if God ſhould now onely take off the exceſſe there was in the Kingdom, though we be pinched for a while, the evill would not be much; our bloud grew very ranke by our fat paſtures. No marvaile though God now letts us bloud. <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaking of exceſſe in meates and drinkes in his time,<note place="margin">Si nunc Adam reſurgeret, &amp; videret hanc inſaniam omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ordinum, profecto credo quod prae ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore tanquam lapis ſtaret. <hi>Luth. in Gen. c. 3.</hi>
                  </note> hath this ſpeach, <hi>If Adam did now riſe again and ſee the madneſſe of all ſorts of men, I beleeve he would ſtand ſenſleſſe through ſudden aſtoniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Few places in the world have been guiltie of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exceſſe then we have been. I have heard of a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in this Kingdome that ſaid, Fifteen hundred pounds a yeare was little enough to keepe him ſweet with linnen. Surely his body was not like <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> The hand of God is at this time heavy upon many of the Nobility and Gentry of the Land, it is moſt righteous that his ſore diſpleaſure ſhould be ſhewn againſt that extreame wanton exceſſe there was among
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113318:23"/> them, proſtrating thoſe good bleſſings of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they abounded, to the ſatisfying their baſe luſts. Let thoſe who yet abound, take heed of this; the ſin in it ſelf it is very great; but when it hath theſe aggravations, it is vile indeed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you abuſe your abundance, when others ſuffer want, when thouſands are ready to periſh for want of neceſſaries, as at this day, how great is then your ſinne before God? it hath now a loud cry in Gods eares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When God hath raiſed you from meane begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, the more remarkable Gods hand appeares in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you abundance, the greater is your ſinne in the abuſe of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If your eſtates have been preſerved through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulties, and that divers times when you have even given all for gone, yet God hath come in and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you the enjoyment of a very full eſtate. What doe you think in your conſciences was Gods end in continuing it to you? Was it that you ſhould yet have farther opportunity to ſatisfie your luſts, and to be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of good, and promoters of evill in the places where you live? God forbid.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If you enjoy your eſtates ſtill, notwithſtanding your conſciences tell you that you have been guiltie of very great abuſe of them: What a wonder is it that God hath not violently rent away all from thee, or thee from what thou haſt thus abuſed all this while; and doſt thou continue to provoke God againſt thee ſtill? is not thy former abuſe of mercies enough, and too much, but wilt thou adde farther? The Lord ſtrike thy heart.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the mercies thou haſt be renewed mercies, after
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113318:24"/> grievous afflictions have been upon thee, after God hath brought thee low, he hath reſtored a great deale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it may be as much, if not more then you had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and will you againe abuſe his mercies? with what face wilt thou look upon God, when thou ſhalt come to give an account of this?</p>
               <p n="6">6. If in times of opportunities of great ſervice, God gives thee abundance, and thou doſt now inſtead of taking the opportunity, mind nothing elſe but to ſatisfie thy luſt, living uſeleſly in all that abundance thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt, thou art vile in Gods eyes; if ſome other had half thy eſtate and means of doing good that thou haſt, how uſefull would he be! God ſhould have much ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice from him, he would bleſſe God for thoſe oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities thou mindeſt not at all. If there be any light of conſcience in thee, oh that it might cauſe ſome miſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoughts to ariſe in thee, that may wound thy heart this day for this thy great ſinne.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If after thou haſt promiſed to God in a ſolemne way, that if he ſhall preſerve thy eſtate, or reſtore thee to the enjoyment of it, thou wilt give it up to his honour; many thouſands in this Kingdome have done thus of late in their earneſt ſeekings of God for their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deliverance. If when God ſhall ſettle thee againe, thou forgetteſt him, regarding little the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good thy engagement to him, know, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne, but ſinne with a high aggravation is upon thee.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If together with thy aboundance the meanes of grace doth alſo abound, whereby thou mightſt learne how to abound, and yet thou doſt not know, nay you little mind it, this ſtill encreaſeth the guilt of thy ſinne. If it were in times of Popery, of darkneſſe, it were not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113318:24"/> ſo much; but being at ſuch a time, the guilt of thy ſinne is raiſed very high.</p>
               <p>Seeing there is ſo much required to this learning how <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> to abound, let thoſe who have not abundance, have their deſires after it moderated; you who are poore, be not too much troubled with the thoughts of your poverty; be not ſo impatient and impetuous in your deſires after riches; doe not envy thoſe who are above you; you ſee what a hazard there is of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage in the enjoying abundance, it may be God ſaw that you did not know how to abound, therefore hath he in mercy denyed that to thee, that in wrath he hath given to others. Let thy heart be quiet, and ſubmit to God, in that condition God hath ſet thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You who have rich friends, you ſee what cauſe you have to pray much for them, they are ſet in ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places, no men have more need of prayers then they.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But the cloſe of all is a word of Exhortation. Set your hearts to theſe truths God hath this day ſet before you. Right Honourable and beloved, conſider what a mercy it is to you, that the greateſt work you have to doe, is to improve mercies. The work of thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands is to get mercies, you have them, and all you have to doe from morning to night is to bleſſe God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and to improve them. If God hath taught you this leſſon to know how to abound, bleſſe his Name. What? all this honour, this great eſtate, and heaven too? What? ſhall theſe things which are means of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing others, help forward my ſalvation? <hi>how excellent is thy loving kindneſſe, oh Lord!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While you are above and abound, let your hearts be kept ſenſible of the meane, low condition of others, of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113318:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113318:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:113318:26"/> their ſtraits, their oppreſſions; let it be your honour to relieve the oppreſſed: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. <hi>As ye abound in every thing, ſee you abound in this grace alſo.</hi> He means the grace of liberality. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.23. it is ſaid of <hi>Araunah,</hi> he gave like a King. Some of you have gloried, that you have ſpent like Princes; let it be rather your glory, that you give like Princes. You have been means to help this oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Kingdome, now, as <hi>Ier. cap.</hi> 28. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. preſented his ſupplication, that he might not return to the houſe of <hi>Ionathan</hi> to die there; ſo we this day to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, let us not be brought again into bondage, and have nothing to lighten our bondage, but a new name.</p>
               <p>Let not violence be uſed to force people to things ſpirituall that they know not, if thoſe who now have but food and raiment ſhould have great penalties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them for not ſubmitting to what they yet have had no meanes to inſtruct them in; how grievous would it bee? The Votes of Parliament are to bee honoured, and the judgement of an Aſſembly of godly and learned men is not to bee ſlighted; but that which muſt ſubject mens conſciences in matters concerning Chriſt and his worſhip, muſt be light from the word. Let not the greatneſſe of your power be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed upon thoſe who doe what they can to know the mind of Ieſus Chriſt, and would fain underſtand and practice more; only they dare not goe further then they ſee Chriſt before them. You cannot ſay men are obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and will not ſee, for what means hath the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Kingdome had to ſee ground out of Scripture for ſuch great changes?</p>
               <p>To uſe force upon people before they have meanes to teach them; is to ſeek to beat the nayle in by the hammer of authority, without making way by the wim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113318:26"/> of inſtruction. Indeed, if you have to deale with rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or ſoft ſappy wood, the hammer only may make the nail enter preſently; but if you meet with ſound wood, with heart of oke, though the hammer, and hand that ſtrikes be ſtrong, yet the nayle will hardly goe in; it will turn crooked or break; or at leaſt, if it enters, it may ſplit that wood it enters into; and if ſo, it will not hold long: you have not your end, conſider you have to deale with Engliſh conſciences; there is no country ſo famous for firm ſtrong okes as England; you will find Engliſh conſciences to be ſo.</p>
               <p>My Lords, you are advanced to high power and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in a Kingdome, where Chriſt hath as many deare Saints of his, as (I had almoſt ſaid) in all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; he expects you ſhould uſe them kindly; they have been faithfull to you, even ſuch as cannot fully come up to you in ſome things you have publiſhed to the world; where hath any one of them (though cryed out upon, as troublers of the Kingdome) falſified their truſt in any thing you have committed to them? you ſit here in peace, and enjoy your honours with abundance of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; in part through the bleſſings of God upon their faithfulneſſe and courage in venturing their lives for you: God forbid you ſhould fall upon them, when your turnes are ſerved by them. Liſten not to any who ſhall whiſper ſuch ſuggeſtions, or boldly vent ſuch things as tend to the exaſperation of your ſpirits this way. There is a great outcry againſt the toleration of all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, &amp; we are willing to joyn againſt ſuch a toleration; but that which fils the mouths of many in this, is the heat of their ſpirits againſt thoſe that differ from them in any thing, that they might with the more ſtrength be able by this to ſtrike at them: ſuffer not your power to be abuſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113318:27"/> to ſerve mens deſigns, be faithfull with God, encourage thoſe that fear him, &amp; God wil take care of your honors; he will doe good to you, and your poſterity after you.</p>
               <p>Doe not hearken to thoſe who tell you theſe men would lay all levell, they would make no difference between the Noble-man, and Trades-man. Yes; we know honour is to bee given to whom honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, God hath made a diſtance between man and man, it is fit it ſhould be acknowledged and obſerved.</p>
               <p>There is no ſuch way to preſerve and increaſe your honours, as by joyning to thoſe whom you are ſure to find faithfull. Account the ſervice of God your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. it is ſaid of Chriſt, he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved honour and glory when there came a voyce from the excellent glory, <hi>This is my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> If it be the glory, the excellent glory of Chriſt, to pleaſe his Father; ſurely it muſt needs then be yours. Let godlineſſe be ſet up by you in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, God is about to advance Religion, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are you that ever you were born, if you be made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall for it.</p>
               <p>Let there be ſomething ſpared out of that abundance God hath given you for the furtherance of the Goſpell; how great the want of able men fitted for the Miniſterie is, the woefull dark places of the Kingdome give ſad te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, except God perſwade the hearts of thoſe who are of eſtates, and have power to help, dreadfull dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will come upon a great part of the Kingdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are aware. There are now many hopefull youths godly, and fitted for the Vniverſitie; in the Weſterne parts; eſpecially, where their parents have been plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſpoiled of their eſtates, now wholly diſinabled to maintaine them at the Vniverſitie. Here are crying objects of charitie, yea, the relieving of them that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113318:27"/> they may bee fitted for the miniſterie, would bee a work fit for the charity and piety of a State to be exerciſed in. If Learning be not maintained, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ignorance, but Barbariſme will come in upon us; the Lord deliver us from that judgement of an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Miniſterie. I this day in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt beſeech you, who have had your eſtates, or a great part of them preſerved, that before you ſleep, you would in your ſecret thoughts ſeparate ſomething for this ſo great, ſo good a work; this would be a good teſtimony of your thankfulneſſe to God for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of them from the common burning. If ſome of you would but ſet aſide ſo much for the promoting of the preaching of Jeſus Chriſt as you have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpent upon your dogs, the bleſſing of many ſoules may be upon you and your poſterity; and if hereafter your ſelves or ſome of your children ſhould come into ſuch congregations, to whom you have been the means of ſending the Goſpel, and you or they ſhould heare that people bleſſing God for thoſe who were the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſo great a bleſſing to their ſoules, would not this be a more delightfull ſound in your or their eares, then a cry of dogs? The ſame charge that heretofore went for that, would help very much in this ſo great a work, ſo worthy of thoſe who profeſſe they live and enjoy all they have, that they may promote the honour of Jeſus Chriſt in their generation.</p>
               <p>And further, I beſeech your Lordſhips, that the door of the preaching of the Goſpel may not be ſtraitned, to keep thoſe out of it, who have hearts to it, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities fitted for it.</p>
               <p>There are at this day, thouſands of Congregations in <hi>England,</hi> who want able Preachers, eſpecially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113318:28"/> parts, as <hi>Cumberland, Weſtmerland,</hi> divers parts of <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> many live like Heathens, ſcarce knowing that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, whether there be a Chriſt, or a holy Ghoſt or no. Now there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers godly, learned young men, who have been called into thoſe parts, and have been willing from their pitty to thoſe poore ſoules, to quit thoſe places, in Lords, Knights, and Gentlemens houſes, where they had comfortable maintenance, to goe into thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but they not having yet ſtudied the Controverſies of Church-government, could not for the preſent ſee ſufficient ground to ſatisfie their conſciences in that way of Ordination, by a company of Miniſters of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Congregations, made up into a Presbytery, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Civill power, limited to the power of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, having no Church act to make them a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, nor no power of government in them; or if go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that extended beyond their miniſterial charge for Word and Sacraments, there being ſo many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in this point, and being new to moſt men, it is no marvaile though young men who are conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and love to ſearch into things that they may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that which may beare up their conſciences, have doubts ariſing, which for the preſent they know not how to ſatisfie themſelves in: Now ſhall theſe who are every way (otherwiſe) fitted for the Miniſtery, be denyed the preaching of the Goſpel in ſuch remote dark places of the Kingdome, though they agree in all other things with their brethren, meerly becauſe they cannot ſatisfie themſelves in this ſcruple of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? God forbid.</p>
               <p>I doe not here ſtand to plead fot a liberty for every man to ſtep up into the Pulpit that will; it is fit men
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113318:28"/> ſhould be examined and approved of, and ſo ſent to this work; but that I plead for, is, that men ſubjecting themſelves to what examination you pleaſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving full teſtimony for learning and godlineſſe, may not be not laid aſide from preaching meerly becauſe they have not that Ordination that is now appointed for ſuch as ſhall enjoy Livings and Eccleſiaſticall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Yea farther, I humbly deſire to preſent this to your Honours, that when men come to be examined for places, the judgement of ſuch who are willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale them, that they might not make diſturbance, may not be drawn forth by having queſtions put to them, What they think of that Presbyterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is now ſet up? and if they yet are not ſatisfied in their conſciences about it, then to be diſmiſſed. I am not now diſputing about what you have determined, God and your Lordſhips have called me to another place, where I have ſpoke my conſcience about it: But this is all I ſay here, Is not this way of Government pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your Lordſhips only, <hi>that it may be?</hi> is it eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by you, as that which ought to be <hi>Jure Divino?</hi> are you then ſo certain of this or that way of Ordination ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that you can take it upon your conſciences it is of ſuch neceſſity, that it is fitter millions of ſouls ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to know Jeſus Chriſt, then this way of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; Government ſhould not be obſerved and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to? If Congregations ſhould make their moanes to God, <hi>Oh Lord, we here ſit in darknes and the ſhadow of death, we have none ſent to us to ſhew us thy wayes, to reveale Jeſus Chriſt, to break the bread of life to us; ſuch able and godly men are willing to come amongſt us out of pitty to our ſouls, but there are queſtions about Ordination and Presbyteries that men
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113318:29"/> who are in power do ſo much ſtand upon and ſtick to (which ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are very controverſall among godly and learned men, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of themſelves have but of late looked into) that becauſe they are ſcrupled, we muſt ſtill continue in our darkneſſe; theſe men who would bring us the light of the Goſpel, muſt not come amongſt us:</hi> would not ſuch a moane as this made to Chriſt from poore ſoules who are ready to receive the Goſpel break your hearts? I am perſwaded it would.</p>
               <p>I have no more to ſay, but to expreſſe my deſires to heaven, that God would crown the enjoyment of your Honours, your power, your eſtates here, with his grace, and your ſoules and bodies with glory before his Saints and bleſſed Angels in the day of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
